Guide to the Rukhl Fishman Papers, 1940-1990
Department of Special Collections
- Series 2. Poetry manuscripts
  - After the rain = nokhn regn (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - There is no joy = nito di freyd (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Not in the pillow = nit in kishn (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Not green = nit grin (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Not like oil on the water = nit vi boyml afn vaser (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Don't be afraid = nit moyre hobn (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Not to be felt with my tongue = nit tsu dertapn mit der tsung (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - No sky = nit keyn himl (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - No = neyn (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Yesterday rain rained = nekhtxt hot regn geregnt (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Owl-face = sove-ponim (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - It's woe = s'iz oy (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - It's just the beginning of summer = s'iz ersht onheyb zumer (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - The night is ifiled with you = s'iz ful mit dir di nakht (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - They towered up around me = s'hobn ufgetoyert arum mir (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Your smile = s'hot dayn shmeykhl (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - No one has yet = s'hot nokh keyner (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - End-of-winter winds = sof vinterdike vintn (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Believers know = s'veysn gleybers (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Nothing will happen this time either = s'vet oykh dos mol gornit geshen (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - The dawn must come = s'vet muzn togn (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Eyes meet = s'trefn zikh oygn (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Empty chatter = s'redt zikh azoy (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - A few bright moments = etlekhe likhtike minutn (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - On my forehead pales = es bleykht af mayn shtern (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - The fingers of my hand blossom = es bliyen di finger af mayne hent (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - An iron head won't help here = es vet do nit helfn keyn ayzener kam (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - It still flames = es flakert alts (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - It rains in through the window = es regnt arayn durkhn fenster (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Apple and nuts on the table = epi un nis afn fish (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - He laughs = er lakht (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Just now = ersht itst (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - I wish I had such a coat = punkt aza mantl vintsh ikh zilth (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Listen to me and be silent = folg mir - un shvayg (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - She doesn't get discouraged = fail zi nit bay zikh (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - There are some good green days = faran gute grine teg (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - I've forgotten what's near and what's far = fargesn noent un vayt (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - For the empty stillness = far der leydiker shtilkayt (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Resentment = fardros (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Why = farvos (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Why must you speak to the point = farvos muz men redn tsu der zakh (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Locking shut our eyes = farshiisn di oygn (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Traveling home = forndik aheym (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Of all the blue skies = far ale bloye himlen (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - One also tires from not working = fun nit arbetn vert men oykh mid (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - My four-legged poem = fir-fisik lid mayne (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Too high, too big = tsu hoykh, tsu groys (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Too many words = tsu Eli verter (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - When I was two years old = tsu tsvey yor (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Too late = tsu shpet (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Will we also = tsi vein mir oykhet (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Don't count = tseyl nit (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - I bit my lip together with = tsebisn in eynem di lip (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Take a good look = kukt zikh gut tsu (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - No one is short of breath = keynem felt nit oys dem otem (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Child, lie down = kind, eyg zilch avek (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - LittIe cow = kiele (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Now you can let down = kenst shoyn aroplozn (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Don't crawl with healthy poems = krikh nit mit gezunte lider (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Black rains = shvartse regns (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - It's past = shoyn adurkh (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - It's more than twenty years = shoyn iber tsvantsik yor (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - It's almost ____ years = shoyn bald ____ yor (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - It's almost a year = shoyn bald a yor (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - It's the third time now = shoyn dos drite mol (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - It's day again = shoyn vider tog (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - You're not guilty = shuldik bistu nit (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Narrow shoulders = shmole pleytses (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - You can lean on me = shpar zilch beser on in mir (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Mirror-writing = shpigl-ksav (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - You play = shpilst zilch (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Keep on writing with both hands = shrayb vayter mit beyde hent (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Several typewritten pages of RF poems in Hebrew translation, prepared by Arye Aharoni of Kibbutz Bet Aifa, in preparation of a bilingual (Hebrew, Yiddish) edition of her poetry. (Box 9, Folder 34)
    -
  - Several typewritten pages of RF poems in original Yiddish, in preparation for bilingual (Hebrew-Yiddish) edition of her poetry. (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Photocopy of a group of RF poems under the title "baym fus fun boym" (At the foot of the tree) which was published in di goldene keyt. Israel. (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Lider tsu mayn geburtstog = Poems for my birthday (Box 9, Folder 36)
    I. Zolst zikh tamid mien = I. You should always try -- II. Mazeldiker hoz = II. Lucky rabbit -- III. Shrayb voyter = III. Write further -- IV. Af trern dar men dokh a sibe = IV. You need a reason for tears -- V. Host gute lerer = You have good teachers -- VI. Nokhn zumer = After the summer
  - Poems (Box 9, Folder 36.1)
    Gedanken zhabes = Froglike -- A groyser hunger = A great hunger -- Vifl koyles hot di nakht = How many voices does the night have -- Ikh tsveyfl = I doubt -- Gedanken zhabes in der finster = Froglike thoughts in the night
  - Poems (Box 9, Folder 36.2)
    Mir vartn = We wait -- Nit tsu dertaph mit der tsung = Not to be felt with my tongue -- S'hobn ufgetoyert avum mir = They towered up around me -- Vint nit avek = Don't go away like the wind -- Ikh shtey far dir = I stand before you
  - Poems (Box 9, Folder 36.3)
    Royter vayn = Red wine -- Tsu hoykh, tsu groys = Too high, too big -- Vikl, farvikl un tulie mir ayn = Wrap me and draw me close -- S'terfn zikh oygn = Eyes meet -- Shpar zikh beser on in mir = You can lean on me
  - Notebook with typescript of Vilde tsig, with poems in Yiddish and Hebrew translation, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - For Eylan's birthday: poem, Hebrew, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Folder for Rukhl Fishman's mss prepared by a member of Kibuz Bet-Alpha who organized her papers after her deathca. 1984 (Box 9, Folder 39)
- Series 3. Clippings
  - Clippings of Rukhl Fishman's published poetry (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Includes: Di Goldene keyt -- Yung Yisroel -- Forverts, plus other publications. Also contains a note from Max Weinreich, 1956. Materials are in Yiddish and Hebrew.
  - Clippings regarding Rukhl Fishman's published poetry & interviews with Rukhl Fishman (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Materials are in Yiddish and Hebrew.
  - Copies of a chapter about Rukhl Fishman from the book "Yiddish in Israel" by Mordkhe Khalomish, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    In Hebrew.
  - Clippings regarding reception for Rukhl Fishman in Philadelphia sponsored by the Rukhl Fishman Book Committee, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    In Yiddish.
  - Clippings regarding reception for Rukhl Fishman's receiving the Itsil Manger Prize, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    In Yiddish, Hebrew, and English.
  - Clippings & obituaries regarding Rukhl Fishman published upon her death, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    In Yiddish and Hebrew.
  - Yortsayt (anniversary of death) announcements published by Joshua A. Fishman and Gella S. Fishman in "Forverts", 1985 - 1991 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Clippings of requests from Joshua A. Fishman and Gella Schweid Fishman for letters and photographs of Rukhl Fishman, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Clippings regarding Theodor Holdheim,n.d. (Box 10, Folder 9)
    In Hebrew, German, and English.
- Series 4. Subject file
  - Materials regarding Rukhl Fishman's poetry. In Yiddishn.d. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Review of Zun iber alts / by Kh. Sh. Kazdan -- Review of Vilde tsig / I. Silberberg
  - Materials regarding the Rukhl Fishman Book Committee & the reception it organized for Rukhl Fishman at the time of her visit to the U.S. in 1962. In Yiddishn.d. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Includes letter from the Committee advertizing "Zun iber alts"; notes by Kh. Barkan for the reception, and ms of Rukhl Fishman's speech at the reception.
  - Materials regarding the Itsik Manger Prize, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Includes the program from the award ceremony and a copy of Rukhl Fishman's speech att eh award ceremony. Materials are in Yiddish and Hebrew.
  - Materials regarding Theodor Holdheim,1985, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Includes published musical compositions and memorial booklet from Kibbutz Bet-Alpha, 1985. Materials are in Hebrew and English.
  - Poster from Avrom Sutzkever's visit to Beyt-Alpha (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Series 5. Personal documents
  - Personal documents. Yiddish, Hebrew, and English (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Includes an invitation to wedding celebration of Rukhl Fishman and Theodor Holdheim, 1954, and a program from Bar-Mitzvah of Avi Fishman, with Rukhl Fishman's notes for her speech.
  - Biographical information about Rukhl Fishman. In English and Hebrew (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Material regarding Rukhl Fishman's medical condition. In Hebrew and English (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Includes article about Rukhl Fishman's case in an Israeli medical journal, 1984. Also includes general information about Lupus.
  - Material regarding Rukhl Fishman's death. In Hebrew,1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Includes speech by Arye Aharoni read at Rukhl Fishman's funeral and copies of letters to Theodor Holdheim at time of Rukhl Fishman's death.
  - Miscellaneous handwritten lists and maps in Yiddish and Hebrew. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Series 6. School & youth activities
  - School notebooks with exercises on Jewish history & Yiddish literature. In Yiddish, 1944 - 1948 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Copies of Der Nayr Dor, a children's magazine edited by Rukhl Fishman. In Yiddish, 1947 - 1948 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Copies of Der Nayr Dor, a children's magazine edited by Rukhl Fishman. In Yiddish, 1948 - 1949 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Materials regarding Rukhl Fishman's activities in various youth clubs. In Yiddish1948 - 1949, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Includes clipping of announcement of symposium of students from the Workmen's Circle School, 1948; poems published in Der Nayer Dor, 1949; and speeches from the Workmen's Circle School & I.L. Peretz Youth Club, n.d.